Indiana University Alpha Pi Zeta records, 1924-1950 C259
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Alpha Pi Zeta records
1924-1950
1924-1928
Indiana University Archives
Alpha Pi Zeta (Indiana University)
C259
.2 cubic feet
The Indiana University chapter of the Alpha Pi Zeta social science fraternity was organized in 1925. The purpose of the society was to encourage the investigation and scholarship in the social sciences. Active membership was open to professors, instructors, staff members, and select graduate students who had shown achievement in social sciences. Collection consists of minutes, financial records, correspondence, membership lists, meeting announcements, and constitutions.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Administrative History
On December 31, 1924, representatives from 14 universities met in Chicago to discuss the establishment of a new social science honorary society. At that meeting, they approved the following resolutions:
A national organisation should be adopted.
Alpha Pi Zeta is a very fitting name for the organisation.
This organisation shall have the character of an honorary society.
It shall encourage investigation and scholarship in the field of the social sciences.
The local societies should exercise a large degree of autonomy as to the methods of work and details of organisation.
Until the question of uniform membership is decided by national action of the society, the matter of the determination of full, associate, honorary and permanent membership shall be left to the chapters according to their separate problems and situations.
The name Alpha Pi Zeta derives from the initials of Aristotle's characterization of man, "anthropos politikon zoon." The purpose of the society was to encourage the investigation and scholarship in the social sciences. Chapters could be established at any educational institution that offered a "considerable amount" of advanced graduate work in the social sciences. Active membership was open to professors, instructors, or staff members of the institution who had shown achievement in social sciences as well as graduate students who had shown "initiative, independence and ability to carry on sustained investigation in one of these sciences."
The IU society met monthly during the school year. At the meetings, they discussed developments in social science scholarship and had featured speakers on a social science topic. Speakers were sometimes IU faculty members, other times campus visitors. By the mid-1930s, meetings were more infrequent, and the minute book reports "No regular meetings were held during 1936-37 or 1937-38. Special meetings were held on call of the President to consider special emergency problems pertaining to the field of the Social Sciences." At their October 3, 1939 meeting, then-President Moffatt moved that meetings be held only upon call of the officers. This is the last entry in the minute book, although there are a few loose minutes dating from the 1939-1940 school year as well as a few items in the collection from later years, including a 1950 meeting announcement. However, due to a lack of minutes, the main activities of the society are not known after 1942.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Correspondence, Administrative files, and Minutes.
Scope and Content Note
The IU society met monthly during the school year. At the meetings, they discussed developments in social science scholarship and had featured speakers on a social science topic. Speakers were sometimes IU faculty members, other times campus visitors. By the mid-1930s, meetings were more infrequent, and the minute book reports "No regular meetings were held during 1936-37 or 1937-38. Special meetings were held on call of the President to consider special emergency problems pertaining to the field of the Social Sciences." At their October 3, 1939 meeting, then-President Moffatt moved that meetings be held only upon call of the officers. This is the last entry in the minute book, although there are a few loose minutes dating from the 1939-1940 school year as well as a few items in the collection from later years, including a 1950 meeting announcement. However, due to a lack of minutes, the main activities of the society are not known after 1942.
The Correspondence series is arranged in chronological order and spans 1925-1942, but the bulk of the correspondence dates from 1925-1928. In the correspondence, there is quite a bit of discussion about the establishment of the group at Indiana University. The correspondence is not only between the members of the Indiana chapter but also between members of the national organization and chapters at other universities throughout the country.
The Administrative files series spans 1924-1950 and includes membership lists for both IU and other chapters throughout the state, reports, meeting announcements, constitutions, and financial records. The financial records primarily consist of notices and payments of dues and receipts for various expenditures. There is one item in the meeting announcements folder that dates to 1950, the only item in the collection dated that late.
The final series, Minutes, 1924-1940, includes 2 folders. The first folder holds a bound minute book that begins with the group's first meeting on December 10, 1924. The last entry in the book is from October 3, 1939. The loose minutes consist of some draft minutes, minutes of the national organization's December 31, 1924 meeting, and some loose minutes that had been tucked into the minute book.
Additional information about the group can be found in Herman B Wells' presidential files.
Acquisition Information
Deposit; Oscar Osburn Winther; 1968; Accessions 1124-1125.
Accession 7986 added February 2013.
Provenance
Deposited by Prof. Oscar Osburn Winther, who was a member and one-time Secretary-Treasurer of the organization.
Social sciences --Societies, etc. --History --20th century --Sources.; Social scientists --Indiana --Archives.; Indiana University -- Faculty -- Intellectual life -- 20th century; Indiana University -- students -- Intellectual life -- 20th century; Alpha Pi Zeta (Indiana University) -- Archives; Alpha Pi Zeta (Indiana University) -- Records and correspondence; Alpha Pi Zeta (Indiana University) -- History -- Sources
- Correspondence, 1925-1942
  - 1925
  - 1926
  - 1927-1928
  - 1930-1942
- Administrative files, 1924-1950
  - Committee on Procedure report, undated
  - Constitutions, 1924-1927; undated
    General
    (for IU and national organization)
  - Financial records, 1925-1927; 1939-1941
  - Meeting announcements, 1925-1930; 1939; 1950
  - Membership lists, 1925-1928; 1939; undated
    (incl. IU and other chapters)
  - "Report to the National Secretary-Treasurer on the local chapter for the year Sep. 1926- June 1927", 17 Sep 1927
- Minutes, 1924-1940
  - Bound volume, 1924-1939
  - Loose minutes, 1924-1927; 1939-1940
    (incl. IU and some national organization meetings)